They're here to save the world.
Ghostbusters is a comedy, fantasy film directed by Ivan Reitman.
After losing their academic posts at a prestigious university, a team of parapsychologists goes into business as
proton-pack-toting "ghostbusters" who exterminate ghouls, hobgoblins and supernatural pests of all stripes.
An ad campaign pays off when a knockout cellist hires the squad to purge her
swanky digs of demons that appear to be living in her refrigerator.
Peter Venkman, played by Bill Murray.
Ray Stantz, played by Dan Aykroyd.
Dana Barrett, played by Sigourney Weaver.
Egon Spengler, played by Harold Ramis.
Louis Tully, played by Rick Moranis.
Janine Melnitz, played by Annie Potts.
Ghostbusters is a 1984 American supernatural comedy film directed by
Ivan Reitman and written by Dan Aykroyd and Harold Ramis.
It stars Bill Murray, Aykroyd, and Ramis as Peter Venkman, Ray Stantz, and Egon Spengler, three
eccentric parapsychologists who start a ghost-catching business in New York City.
It also stars Sigourney Weaver and Rick Moranis, and features Annie Potts,
Ernie Hudson, and William Atherton in supporting roles.
Based on his fascination with spirituality, Aykroyd conceived Ghostbusters as a project starring himself and
John Belushi, in which they would venture through time and space battling supernatural threats.
Following Belushi's death in 1982, and with Aykroyd's concept deemed financially impractical, Ramis was
hired to help rewrite the script to set it in New York City and make it more realistic.
It was the first comedy film to employ expensive special effects, and Columbia Pictures, concerned about
its relatively high $25–30 million budget, had little faith in its box office potential.
Filming took place from October 1983 to January
1984, in New York City and Los Angeles.
Due to competition for special effects studios among various films in development at the time, Richard Edlund used part of the budget to found
Boss Film Studios, which employed a combination of practical effects, miniatures, and puppets to deliver the ghoulish visuals.
Ghostbusters was released on June 8, 1984, to critical
acclaim and became a cultural phenomenon.
It was praised for its blend of comedy, action, and horror, and
Murray's performance was often singled out for praise.
It earned at least $282 million worldwide during its initial theatrical run and was the
second-highest-grossing film of 1984 in the United States and Canada, and the then-highest-grossing comedy ever.
It was the number-one film in US theaters for seven consecutive weeks and one
of only four films to gross more than $100 million that year.
Further theatrical releases have increased the worldwide total gross to around $370
million, making it one of the most successful comedy films of the 1980s.
In 2015, the Library of Congress selected it for
preservation in the National Film Registry.
Its theme song, "Ghostbusters" by Ray Parker Jr., was also a number-one hit.
With its effect on popular culture, and a dedicated fan following, the success of
Ghostbusters launched a multi-billion dollar multimedia franchise.
This included the popular animated television series The Real Ghostbusters (1986), its follow-up Extreme
Ghostbusters (1997), video games, board games, comic books, clothing, music, and haunted attractions.
Ghostbusters was followed in 1989 by Ghostbusters II, which fared less well financially and
critically, and attempts to develop a second sequel paused in 2014 following Ramis's death.
After a 2016 reboot received mixed reviews and underperformed financially, a second sequel to the 1984 film,
Ghostbusters: Afterlife (2021), was released, followed by Ghostbusters: Frozen Empire (2024).
The film explores themes of new york city, environmental protection
agency, library, supernatural, paranormal phenomena.
The tone is lighthearted.